<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honour of kings vindicated and asserted In a sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sr. Patrick Drummond, late Conservator of the Priviledges of the Scots nation in the Netherlands, togeter [sic] with a considerable number of merchants, masters, and common sea-men from several places, the 3. of May 1661. stilo novo, being his Majesties coronation day. By Mr. Thomas Mowbray Minister of the Gospel at the Stapel-Port in Camp-veet.</title>
            <author>Mowbray, Thomas, minister of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2995A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829540</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829540</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51533)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1920:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honour of kings vindicated and asserted In a sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sr. Patrick Drummond, late Conservator of the Priviledges of the Scots nation in the Netherlands, togeter [sic] with a considerable number of merchants, masters, and common sea-men from several places, the 3. of May 1661. stilo novo, being his Majesties coronation day. By Mr. Thomas Mowbray Minister of the Gospel at the Stapel-Port in Camp-veet.</title>
                  <author>Mowbray, Thomas, minister of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Berry, dwelling near the English Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Middelburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Honour of Kings Vindicated and Aſſerted.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached before the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Patrick Drummond,</hi> late Conſervator of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> togeter with a conſiderable number of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Maſters, and common Sea-men from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places, the 3. of <hi>May</hi> 1661. <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſties <hi>Coronation Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               </hi> THOMAS MOWBRAY <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel at the Stapel-Port in</hi> Camp-veer.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Reddite quae ſunt Caeſaris, Caeſari.</l>
               <l>An neſcis longas Regibus eſſe manus?</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>MIDDELBURGH, Printed by <hi>Thomas Berry,</hi> dwelling near the Engliſh Exchange. 1663.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable the Commiſſioners of the Royal Broughs within the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the undoubted and unqueſtionable Patrons of the <hi>Scots</hi> Church, at their Stapel-Port in <hi>Camp-veer.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T</hi> may ſeem very ſtrange that this Sermon after two years lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and above, ſhould now in this ſimple, and poor dreſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to ſhow it ſelf, to your judicious eyes, and cenſure, like a thing born out of due time, I hope the meanneſs of its ſtrain, not being adorned with the fair flooriſhes of humane eloquence, doth ſufficiently proclaime to all ingenuous ſpirits, that neither pride, nor vanity hath brought it to this publick view: But to ſatiſfie your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and all Men of Candor, be pleaſed to take notice of the true reaſon of this my preſent attempt, which indeed is to obſtruct and (if poſſible) to overturn ſome Mens <hi>miſrepreſentations</hi> of me in the poynt of fidelitie, and loyaltie to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and that to Men of <hi>eminencie</hi> and great <hi>truſt</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> I ſhall accuſe no Man, I pray that the Lord may forgive them, and I do heartily, and freely forgive them alſo: Only as the ſad imputation of diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to his <hi>Sacred Majeſtie,</hi> is a moſt grievous burthen, to an honeſt Man, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of my coat, who has been even in the worſt of times indeavouring loyalty ſo for as he might, with the hazard of life, and what elſe is moſt pretious; ſo I think its lawful for me, yea altogether neceſſary (and therein I wrong no Man) to Apologize for my ſelf, and no other defence ſhall I uſe for my own vindication, then this following Sermon, wherein (how mean ſoever) your Honours, and every Man elſe, who will be pleaſed to peruſe it, may ſee what is my manner of Doctrine in reference to that obedience, and ſubmiſsion, which every good Subject ows to his Soveraigne, the <hi>Kings ſacred Majeſty,</hi> and to this preſent Government, as it is now eſtabliſhed. It may be preſumed, that a loyal Man in the Pulpit, will not be diſloyal out of it: and houever a ſound Judgment, and a right Practice
<pb facs="tcp:33980:4"/> are not alwaeis inſeparable, according to that old Saying, <hi>Video meliora, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boque, deteriora ſequor,</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> hope Chriſtian charity will pleade at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours hands, and every one elſe that ſhall ſee this Paper, to think the beſt of me, until you have ſufficiently informed your ſelves of me, and when that ſhall once be, I truſt that your good opinion of me will be confirmed. I know that this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſhall meet with no better entertainment then others of a more elaborate, and Judicious compoſure have done before, but let <hi>prejudice, malice,</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquie</hi> ſpeak what they can, I hope there is nothing contained here, but ſound Truths conſiſtent with <hi>Scripture</hi> and the judgment of Orthodox Divines, both <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>moderne,</hi> which truly I have ſet down very faithfully, as I found them ſcattered here and there in their Writings. Let it not offend your Honours, that I have ſheltered this worthleſs piece under your Names; to whom ſhould I flie for <hi>Patrocinie,</hi> if not to my <hi>Patrons?</hi> The experience of your Honours kindneſs hath imboldned me to caſt my ſelf upon you, and to expect a favourable acceptation of the firſt fruits of my weak labours, which in reaſon you may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge as yours, and (ſo far as equity will perſwade) to countenance me in the diſcharge of my <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> here. I am affraid (if I ſhould inlarge) to meet with that of the <hi>Cynick, Cloſe your gates, leſt your City run out,</hi> and therefore I ſhall winde up all with this, that the Lord would powre out upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you, the Spirit of your callings, that as at home, ſo here, by your God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unanimous Counſels Piety may be advanced, and Trade may flouriſh, which ſhall be for a Name that will not be forgotten, So prays</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours much obliged Servant in the Goſpel, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
                  </hi> Thomas Mowbray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33980:4"/>
            <head>The Honour of Kings Vindicated and aſſerted.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</bibl>
                  <p>Honour the King.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not unknown to you (I ſuppoſe) why we are here ſo ſolemnly conveened at this time, our duty to God, our duty to our Soveraigne, our duty to our Country, our duty to thoſe amongſt whom we live for the time, and and generally to the whole Chriſtian World, the duty we owe to our ſelves if we would be accounted loyal, faithful, and honeſt Subjects, all calls aloud upon us, this day to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute our indeavours for the ſolemnization of it, and that in regard of that much longed for action, this day with ſo great Triumphs, and acclamations performed, the <hi>Coronation of His Majeſtie,</hi> the happie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof, I hope ſhall indure ſo long as time ſhall laſt. A long and a dark night of confuſions, and horrible oppreſſions, when there was no <hi>King</hi> in our <hi>Iſraëll,</hi> every man doing what ſeemed good in his own eyes, hath ſore broken and affrighted us, and who is there that had the leaſt ſpark of loyalty in his breaſt, and any ſenſe of Religion, that did not ſee the horrour of it? Now may we ſing, the night ſhaddows are blown away, the day appeareth, and the Beaſts of prey are retired to their dens, where I hope they ſhall not long lodge in ſecuritie, yea the Sun is riſen, and is going on towards the mid-day; doe we not begin to feel his heate? And is there not much more good laid up for us, which we may warrantably expect, if we will carry our ſelves as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Loyal Subjects? Well then ſeeing all (next to Gods moſt free,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33980:5"/> and undeſerved favour) flows from the happy Reſtauration of our <hi>King</hi> to that which alwaies in regard of birth, and a moſt juſt, free, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute title of Inheritance was, (even in the worſt of times) his; hath God (I ſay again) bleſſed and honoured us with a <hi>King,</hi> and ſet the <hi>Royal Diademe</hi> this day upon his ſacred Head? have we not then reaſon, to bleſs God for it, to rejoyce in this day which the Lord hath made, and to <hi>Honour our King,</hi> doubling and redoubling our cries <hi>God ſave the King?</hi> Certainly if <hi>Samuel</hi> did but judge it a reaſonable requeaſt of <hi>Saul,</hi> (whom yet God had rejected from being King, becauſe he had rejected the Word of the Lord) and that was to honour him before the Elders of his People, and before <hi>Iſraël,</hi> leaſt they obſerving <hi>Samuel</hi>'s ſlighting of him, ſhould happen to deſpiſe him, while he held the Throne. Shall we not much more look upon it as a thing moſt reaſonable to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our <hi>King,</hi> whom the Lord hath gratiouſly reſtored, and that in the ſight and preſence of ſtrangers, that they may alſo learn to fear, and to honour him. It is true, all that we can doe this way is but litle, but if our myte be beſtowed, with a willing mind, and a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart, it ſhall be as acceptable as a greater gift from theſe who is more able to give. But I will not longer hold you up in the entrie, let us next ſee how we are to perform this dayes work in <hi>Honouring our King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words read, and the reſt of this Verſe, are a concluſion of an Exhortaiton laid down in the 13. Verſe, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whither to the King as Supreame, or unto Governours, as unto them, that are ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c. where the Apoſtle holds forth the duty of Subjects towards their Superiours, and here again doth repeate, the Subſtance of a Subjects duty to his Soveraign, and withall doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to thoſe to whom he wrote, the deſcription of an abſolute Subject or Citizen, in all his relations, and tells them in a few words, what would make a Chriſtian, living in humane Societies, eminent for exactneſs of his behaviour; for, he in theſe words forms him in his cariage to all men, to good men, to <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>King,</hi> and ſo his charge enjoyns Firſt courteſie to all men. 2. Charity to Godly men. 3. Piety to God. 4. Loyalty to the King. And of this laſt am I (God willing) to ſpeak at this time, <hi>Honour the King.</hi> Before I fall upon the particular open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of this Duty, we may obſerve ſomething from the Connexion of it, with what goes before, which is.</p>
            <p>Obſerv. <hi>That the Fear of God, and the Honour of the King are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſtent, the one of them does not hinder the other;</hi> a man may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33980:5"/> be a very pious man, and yet a very Loyal Subject, ſee the Apoſtle doth immediatly joyn them together, <hi>Fear God, Honour the King.</hi> So <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 24.21. <hi>My ſon fear thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> Our Saviour alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. tells us that the doing of our duty to God, doth not hinder the doing of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the King; for he, in the matter of Tribute joyns both together, <hi>Render unto Caeſar, the things which are Caeſars, and unto God, the things which are Gods.</hi> He who hath commanded the one hath alſo commanded the other, to wit, God himſelf, and his Commandments, are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent. Again, how ſhall our Piety to God be manifeſted, but by our Loyalty to the King, Gods Vicegerent, and Deputie here upon Earth? And how can we indeed be Loyal to the King, if we be not Pious towards God? This is a thing impoſſible, there may be indeed a ſhew of Loyalty, and fair pretenſes, but ſtill for our own ends, we ſhall never look upon this as a matter of Conſcience, to ſubmit our ſelves for the Lords ſake, which will only make a man fixt, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in this his duty come what may; whereas wicked, impious men, let them pretend what they pleaſe to Loyaltie, they have treacherous hearts within them, which will when the occaſion offers ſoon diſcover it ſelf, as wofull experience in our own times hath plentifully manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. But which is much to be wondred at, that they who pretends to Piety ſhould ſo much ſhew themſelves diſloyal, as if to be Pious, and Loyal were not at all conſiſtent: It was the glory ſomtime of the Primitive Chriſtians, to be moſt Loyal, and faithful to their Kings, and Emperours, for which many of them was advanced to Places of great truſt: but in theſe latter times Chriſtianity hath been diſgraced, and the glory of the Proteſtant Religion never before beſpotted with this infamous note of diſloyaltie, hath been and is much impaired with thoſe who are without, and our Country and Country-men overloaded, with diſgraceful reproaches amongſt the Nations; I wiſh that now while the occaſion is offered, they may redeem their credit, by ſome fair, and manifeſt token of their Loyalie, which in ſome meaſure may be equivalent to their former overſight, and failings, being led away with the fair ſhews, and pretences of Religion, and liberty, which did directly lead them to a baſe ſlavery, and almoſt to the loſs of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to a deſtable Anarchy; who was the firſt Plottets and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of this, the Lord will in his own time find out, when they ſhall periſh in the gainſaing of Core.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeak to the Duty it ſelf, <hi>Honour the King.</hi> In handling
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33980:6"/> whereof I ſhall obſerve this order, Firſt I ſhall clear the words, and remove ſome Objections which may here be moved. 2. I ſhall ſhew you wherein the Honour of the King conſiſts, and how we are to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him? 3. Why we are to do this? Where we ſhall ſee that this is not an arbitrary thing, but an abſolute, and an expreſs Duty lying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. Laſtly, I ſhall apply this Doctrine according to our preſent ſtate, and condition.</p>
            <p>For the Firſt, <hi>Honour the King,</hi> the Vulgar Tranſlation reads it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence the King, make him honourable, <hi>Regem honorificate,</hi> but in the Greek the word is one and the ſame in the beginning, and ending of the Verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, honour all men, and honour the King. Hereby is underſtood, a particular, and a ſpecial kind of honour which we are to give to the <hi>King,</hi> not ſuch an honour only as we are to give to all thoſe amongſt whom we live indifferently, whither good, or bad, religious or prophane, acquaintance or ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhunning that which juſtly may give offence, and doing that whereby we may gain them, by our reſpectful ſpeeches, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, ſhewing our ſelves alwaies meek, and courteous, yet never to juſtifie the Wicked, nor to condemne the Rightous. I ſay it is another kind of honour which we are to give to the King, which is eſpecially <hi>honor obſequii,</hi> as you ſhall afterwards (God willing) hear.</p>
            <p>But it may be here aſked, whom the Apoſtle means by the word <hi>King?</hi> Such as underſtands the Epiſtle to be written to the Jews, may perhaps conceave, that the Kings that ruled by deputation in <hi>Judea</hi> ſhould be meant, ſuch as was <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Agrippa.</hi> But for as much as the Jews were ſcattered through the Provinces, and thoſe Provincial Jews were moſt in quiet, and ſeeing alſo it is like, that the Epiſtle was written to all Chriſtians, both Jews and Gentiles, therefore by the King he meant <hi>Ceſar.</hi> And if ſo, another doubt may ariſe greater then the former. The <hi>Romans</hi> hated the name of a King, and <hi>Ceſar</hi> was an Emperour.</p>
            <p>Now to this divers things are anſwered. Firſt, That though the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governour was an Emperour; yet the Apoſtle knowing by ſome Divine inſtinct, that the moſt Monarchies in the World in all Ages, would reſt in the title of <hi>King,</hi> therefore he uſes that title, which may moſt concern the Elect in all Ages.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though amongſt the <hi>Romans;</hi> the title of King was not uſed, yet the <hi>Grecians</hi> in whoſe Language he did write, did familiarly uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we tranſlate <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33980:6"/>3. The Apoſtle might have reſpect to the ſignification of the word, as unto a word which was moſt effectual to note the higheſt dignity amongſt men; for it notes him, who is the ſtay and foundation of the People or Commonwealth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> id eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and though am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious men ſought new titles, as higher, yet the Apoſtle knew, that this was moſt majeſtical, and honourable: whereas the tearme ef Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, in the ſignification of it may agree to any ſubordinate rule, who governs, or commands over men.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It may be that the Apoſtle knowing the hypocriſie of theſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, (who only diſclaimed the name of Kings, to avoid the hatred of the people, and yet ſought the full right of Kings, ſo to deſtroy the liberty of the people) giveth the name they ſought in ſubſtance, though not in tearm.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Apoſtle may name Kings, to prevent Rebellion in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which either ſhould fear ſuch as affected the title, or live under ſuch as profeſſed themſelves to be Kings, and ſo the meaning is that he would have them even to obey Kings, how hateful ſoever naturally that kind of Government did ſeem unto them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Apoſtle maketh mention of Kings, as the laſt kind of Government. A Monarchy being in many reſpects the moſt excellent form of Government, as coming neereſt to the ſimilitude of God, who is not only one in Nature, but one in Government alſo: and is moſt agreeable to Nature which doth affect Unity, as well in the body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick as in the body Natural.</p>
            <p>Thus of the Reaſon why the Apoſtle uſes this tearm, and whom he means by this word King? For it is indefinitly ſet down, and ſo it ſhews that this honour belongs to all Kings in the ſubſtance of it, whither he be King of one City or many, whither he be a Jew, or Gentile, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or Pagan, Heretical, or Orthodoxal, young or old, vertuous, or vitious.</p>
            <p>Hence we may know how to reſolve that doubt which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by ſome concerning the repetition of this Duty here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, it was ſaid before that we ſhould ſubmit our ſelves to the King as Supreame, which is the ſame honour that is required of us in our Text, <hi>(Honour the King)</hi> is not hier a Tautologie, may ſome ſay? I Anſwer not, there is not a word in all Scripture ſet down in vain, the reaſon hereof is, the Apoſtle here is writing to Chriſtians, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour under whom they lived, was a Heathen, and a Pagan, profane and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33980:7"/> diſſolute, now leaſt they ſhould think, that they were not bound to give that ſame due honour, and obedience to them as to Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Kings, therefore the Apoſtle as is ſaid, doth again particularly make mention of this Duty, whereby he ſhews that difference in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion doth not make voyd the Kings lawful Authority, as it is in the Confeſſion of Faith, we are to honour him though a Turk or Heathen, as much as if he were one of the ſame Religion with us, and one of the moſt ſincere Profeſſors of that Religion, whoſe actions in every point were anſwerable to his Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The words thus cleared, and theſe doubts being removed, holds forth unto us this Doctrine and Leſſon, which is and ought to be the Duty of this day, and alwaies, and that is briefly this.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That if we would be eminent for exactneſs in our diſpoſition, and continual cariage, then muſt we ſtudie, and indeavour as Piety towards God, ſo Loyalty towards the King;</hi> we muſt (I ſay) as <hi>fear God, ſo honour the King.</hi> For the better clearing of this, I ſhall firſt let you ſee, wherein the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King conſiſts, and how we are to honour him? 2. Why we are to do this? And laſtly, I ſhall apply.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, We are to honour the King theſe three wayes, 1. In our hearts. 2. In our words. 3. In our works.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay we are to honour the King in our hearts, which is to be manifeſted theſe two wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt we muſt not curſe the King, no not in ſecret, no: not in our thoughts, we muſt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of our People. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. Which Law prohibeteth not only imprecations and ſeditious railings, (which is an Helliſh impiety, though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſecret) but alſo all baſe, and irreverend uſage of the King in our thoughts, and rather then Tranſgreſſours of this Law ſhould goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. that the birds of the air, ſhall carry the voyce, and that which hath wings ſhall utter the matter, therefore curſe not the King, no not in thy thought.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the King commands any thing, that ſeems to others, or to us, harſh, inconvenient or doubtful, we muſt honour the King by interpreting his Laws, in the beſt ſenſe. If Love muſt not think evil, but hope the beſt things of all men, then much more of Kings. It were greatly to be wiſhed, that this Note might enter into ſome mens breaſts, they would then be affraid to charge ſo much evil upon the Kings Ordinances, not only when they might find a fairer ſenſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33980:7"/> but oftentimes expreſſly againſt the intent, and meaning of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. How guilty have thoſe among us who in this particular ſhould have been directers, and informers of others, I leave to all men who knew any thing of the late proceedings with the King to judge, I am ſure a School-maſter did never more narrowly examine his Scholers Theame, or Verſion to ſee what was right or wrong in it, then the Letters, and Declarations, both of the late martyred King, and of this, have been ſearched, and canvaſſed by theſe to whom they came; here was a back-door, and there was an evaſion, here was too great ſtrictneſs, there was too great liberty, and ſtill ſome one thing, or another, (I dare ſay which was never intended,) hindered that there could be no right underſtanding, ſuch jelouſies, fears, and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, never, or ſeldom ends fair, as we have well ſeen by woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as we muſt honour the King in our thoughts, ſo alſo in our words. Firſt by reverend ſpeeches, to them, and of them. God hath engraven ſo large and fair a character of his Imperial Image in their Forheads (ſayes <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) as muſt be ſacred in the hearts of all, and bind not their hands only but their tongues alſo to the good behaviour, and that for ever; Invectives, and contumelious ſpeeches againſt an equal, or inferiour are ever odious, but againſt a Prince intollerable. Is it meet for a child to ſnap up his natural Parents, although they ſhould deſerve a ſharp reproof? Doth not the Apoſtle forbid Servants ſo much as ſaucily to anſwer their Maſter again although provoked? Saith he it is ſuch as have good, and gentle Maſters? Doubtleſs he ſaith it to ſuch as are under froward, and wicked Tyrants. And is it fit then to ſay to a King, thou art wicked, and to Princes ye are ungodly? as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Job,</hi> Cap. 34.18. Princes may not before others be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be ſo wicked, as perhaps they be, care muſt be had of their honour, and fame, ſaith Wiſe, and Judicious <hi>Calvin,</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> 34.18. what ever their converſation be, their place requires it, though their actions ſhould not deſerve it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt honour the King in our words, by a thankful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the good that is in them, and we receive from them. The Apoſtle writing to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 Epiſt. 2.2. ſetteth down the bleſſings which a People enjoyes by means of their good Kings, which are three, Peace, Godlineſs, and Honeſty, each of theſe is a great bleſſing. Firſt Peace if we reſpect deliverance from Enemies abroad, is a great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33980:8"/> therefore <hi>Arabia</hi> was called <hi>Foelix,</hi> becauſe the People lived in continual Peace, and had their Towns unwalled; how happy was the Government of <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> when the Bees made their byves in the Souldiers Helmets, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen men brake their Swords into Mattocks, and their Spears into Plow ſhars; but they priſe the Olive-branch of Peace beſt, who have had long experience of the ſcourge of Warr.</p>
            <p>Again, Peace is a great bleſſing if we reſpect quiet from diſcords at home: an inteſtine Warr in many reſpects is worſe then a foraigne, eſpecially becauſe it is betwixt Brethren, and ſuch Warr <hi>taro ſenecit, ira fratrum acerbiſſima,</hi> and therefore (ſacys <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 18.19.) <hi>a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offended, is harder to be won then a ſtrong City: and there contentions are like the bars of a Caſtle.</hi> There is leſs hope of a compoſition here, then if it were with ſtrangers. It was therefore good counſel which <hi>Joſeph</hi> gave to his Brethren, <hi>fall not out by the way:</hi> and that <hi>Moſes</hi> gave to the two <hi>Hebrews</hi> when they were at odds, and he would have made them one again, <hi>Sirs ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong one to another?</hi> Now this publick and private Peace, we enjoy under good Kings, and who doth enjoy it more then we, under our own King? We have been for many years whirled about with tumultuous broyles, and covered with a deluge of Warr. Now the Dove hath found an Olve leaf, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting place, our Motto may be <hi>Aequova tuta filent,</hi> and by whom have we this, if not by (next to God,) our King? whoſe preſence like the Sum at moon-day hath diſſipated theſe dark, and thick clouds, which not long ſince darkened the whole Iſland of <hi>Britaine:</hi> have we not then reaſon to <hi>Honour our King,</hi> and that by a thankful acknowledgment, that by him under God, we enjoy this great quietneſs? You mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and Seamen, and generally all of us who reſids here muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelves bound to <hi>honour our King:</hi> it is ſcarſe paſt twelve Moneths yet, when you could not without great hazard of Pyrats, and Capers paſs to and fro about your buſineſs, unleſs you had been behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to Strangers, and that at your own charge too, for Convoyes: Now there is none more free then you, and I am ſure if we will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this as a benefit, by demeaning your ſelves as good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, you will ſhow your ſelves moſt unthankful, and the very ſtones in the ſtrees ſhould cry out againſt you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond benefit mentioned by the Apoſtle is Godlineſs. A good Prince like <hi>Canutus</hi> before the Conqueſt, makes Laws by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his Sages, binding his Subjects to one Rule of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33980:8"/> he will have but one Chriſt, one Creed, one Religion, one Faith, one Baptiſm; he will not have <hi>Diana,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>'s Preaching, the Philiſtins <hi>Dagon,</hi> and Gods Arke, nor the Goſpel, and Popery to ſtand together, nor will he light one candel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God and another to the Devil, no compoſition, no confuſion of Religions, as there was Languages at the building of <hi>Babel.</hi> Have we not ſeen much of this, ſince our Kings happy Reſtauration that damnable Tolleration once paſt in an Act hath received its deaths wounds, Uniformity in the true Religion commanded, and by that we have ſeen, we have reaſon to expect, that all ſhall be well, and Popery as much diſcourted as the vvorſt of the Fanaticks, vvhich is the only fear novv. Is it not manifeſt that our King hath begun his Reign well, like another <hi>Joſias</hi> paſſing Acts for the ſuppreſſing of Drunkenneſs, and ſwearing, and night walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the predominant ſins of all Courts? By which we may warrantably preſume, that as he increaſes in ſtrength and power, ſo the vigour, and force of ſuch Acts, and many other as good ſhall be ſeen, and felt, to the danting and overturning of all thoſe who preſumptuouſly dare control them.</p>
            <p>The third benefit is Honeſty, A good Prince hath a care, that there be juſt and honeſt dealing betwixt man, and man, that he that hath much (ſetting Honeſty aſide,) doth not tyrannize over him that hath little, that doth not by fraud and violence, (holding that which is not his) convert that which is anothers to his own uſe: that People live not like beaſts, but Honeſtly, and Uprightly one with another. Theſe three I ſay are great bleſſings, which we enjoy under good Princes, and the want of any of them is a great blemiſh in the Common-wealth; Peace without Godlineſſe is but Security, and Godlineſſe without Honeſty is but Hypocriſie, Honiſty without Godlineſſe is but Paganiſm, and a gliſtring ſin, neither Godlineſſe and Honeſty without Peace can be well maintained; Godlineſſe is the ſum of the firſt Table, Honeſty the ſum of the ſecond, Peace a happy maner of enjoying both.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we muſt honour the King in our vvords, by praying to God for him, <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all, Prayers, interceſsions, and giving of thanks, be made for all men: For Kings, and all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet, and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe, and honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. Certainly if we will conſider the great and weighty charge of Kings, how all depends upon them, we will never refuſe to pay
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33980:9"/> them this honour: if we would conſider the great commoditie and profit, which we enjoy under their happy, and peaceable Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as you have now heard a part of it,) we could not but be earneſt with God in their beha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that the Lord would give unto them the Spirit of Wiſdom, and Underſtanding, and of the fear of the Lord, that they may know how to go out, and in before us, that Religion may flouriſh, Vertue advanced, and Vice may be curbed, and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed, this moved <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 72.1.2. to pray thus in the behalf of his Son <hi>Solomon, Give the King thy Judgments O God, and thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the Kings Son. He ſhall judge thy People with righteouſneſs, and thy poor with judgment.</hi> And for this end alſo we muſt intreate God that he would remove far from him wicked, baſe flatterers, who ſeeks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but themſelves, <hi>that ſo his Throne may be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Prov. 25.5. fauning flatterie is an occupation fitter for a Dog then a Man: and Princes have no Traitours like to flatterers; if treacherie againſt the Soul be more perilous, then that againſt the body, I am ſure no ſin in the Book of God hath more woes attending it, then this. Have we not then reaſon to honour the King this day by praying for him, that he may be preſerved from ſuch; aſſuredly ſo long as ſuch are in power, and place, the Throne will be but in a tottering condition; <hi>but let mercy and truth preſerve the King, for his Throne is upholden by mercy,</hi> Prov. 20.28. and whoſover will not thus pray for the King, let his tongue cleave to the roofe of his mouth, and let him be noted as one that will not <hi>Honour the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third way how we muſt honour the King is in our Works, and that firſt by a reverend geſture, and cariage while before him, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of this it was not lawful ſo much as to laugh in the Court of the <hi>Areopagits,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Cenſurs diſgraded a Burges for yaunig too wide in their preſence, and not only owe we this reverence in regard of an Oath, but we are bound unto it by Nature, in token of which God hath given to Kings three eſpecial enſigns of honour, a Crown of Gold, a Scepter of Righteouſneſs, and a Sword of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt honour the King in our works, by paying Tributes, and Cuſtoms, for the neceſſarie maintenance of his Eſtate. <hi>Render to all their dues</hi> (ſacys the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.6, 7.) <hi>Tribute to whom Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom is due, this way</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſayes in the ſame place) <hi>do we manifeſt our ſubjection to, and honouring of them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33980:9"/> even by paying Tribute to them; for they are Gods Miniſters attending upon this very thing.</hi> Therefore our Saviour rather then he ſhould be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in this Duty, he commanded a Fiſh to pay it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. Chriſt doth not ſay (ſpeaking of this Tribute paying) <hi>date,</hi> as if it were a free voluntary gift, but <hi>reddite quae ſunt Caeſaris Caeſari.</hi> It is a due, and their proper good, and therefore as one ſayes upon theſe ſelf-ſame words, to withhold that which the Parliament grants, or to value our ſelves at leſs then we are worth, that ſo we may pay the leſs, is no leſs then theft, and theſe who goes about to deceive the Kings Cuſtomers, and grudges at his neceſſary, and lawfull impoſitions are theeves, not ſuch as are honourers of the King. And how will this ſtand with that ordinary practice which (as I am informed,) you have at your Waſhings, (as you call them) I leave to your ſelves to judge, I wiſh that there were no more of it, it is baſe, and I am ſure contrary to every good Subjects Duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not only muſt we honour the King with our goods, but in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him with our lives for his defence; the People will not have King <hi>David</hi> adventure himſelf in the Warr, but put their lives in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to ſave him harmleſſe. The two Tribes <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to ſhew their valour, and fidelitie, will fight againſt the other Tribes though their Brethren; for <hi>Rhehoboam</hi> their King. <hi>I</hi> read in the Engliſh Hiſtory that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, being at the ſiege of a certain Caſtle in <hi>Schropſhire,</hi> had been ſtruck through with an Arrow, had not a certain Noble-man put himſelf between the Arrow and the King, and ſo received the Arrow with his own death. VVhat ſhall we then ſay to theſe who are ſo far from hazarding their lives for the <hi>King,</hi> that they will adventure their lives to make him away, as <hi>Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Caſsius,</hi> who ſlew <hi>Ceſar</hi> in the Senate houſe: but much more to be abhorred are theſe who under the colour of a Law will bring their King to a Scaffold, as theſe moſt notorious, and Treacherous Rigicids of late did, an act which cannot be paralelled in any Hiſtory either Sacred, or profane ſince the beginning; I am ſure though this indeed did one way tend to the honour of the King, that he was the Martyr of the People, whoſe remembrance ſhall be alwaies famous, freſh, and odoriferous; yet no other thing was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by them, but his great diſhonour, and by that fatal blow to put an end to all Kings for ever in <hi>BRITAINE,</hi> and as they dealt with the Father, ſo they reſolved to deal with the Heir if ever he came
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33980:10"/> in their hands, but ſome of them did live to ſee themſelves arraigned at his Barr, and to receive the juſt reward of their for ever to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred treachery, and murther; <hi>So let all ſuch periſh, O Lord, that others may henceforth fear to ſtrech forth their hands againſt the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, vve muſt honour the King by yeelding, and ſubmitting to their Ordinances, preferring obedience to ſacrifice, or to the cenſures of any Man whatſoever, the <hi>Kings</hi> vvill muſt be done <hi>aut à nobis, ant de nobis,</hi> either of us, or upon us, vvhen their Lavvs agrees vvith Gods Lavvs, then muſt vve be Agents, vvhen they are diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Patients. The Conſcience cannot be tyed by any Lavv of Man to do that vvhich in it ſelf is ſinful, here vve acknovvledge no Superiour but God himſelf, in ſuch caſes it is better to obey God then Men, yet in not obeying the Ordinances and Commandments of the <hi>King</hi> though bad, vve are to ſubmit our ſelves to the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment vvhich ſhall be laid upon us, for our not obeying, becauſe the Lavvs of Men do bind the utter man properly; It is more Chriſtian to ſuffer thus, then to raiſe Arms againſt the Magiſtrate upon any account, though vve may have ſufficient Forſes and ſtrength ſo to do. As for things indifferent, vvhich are commanded, or things not clearly knovvn to us, as bearing a double ſenſe, and ambignous; vve muſt conſtruct the <hi>Kings</hi> Commands in the beſt ſenſe, and albeit vve are to do nothing doubtingly, yet it is better to give obedience, beleeving that vvhich is commanded to be lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then by ſuppoſing the contrary to refuſe the Command; for this certainly is a greater evil, then poſſibly is imagined. Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or doubting of the lavvfulneſſe of things is no diſcharge for obedience; vvhat confuſion this hath brought into the Church and Commonvvealth our times doth afford inſtances enough. If vve refuſe to obey vvhen things unlavvfull, and ſinfull, (as being either againſt the Lavv of God, the Lavv of Nature, the fundamentall Lavvs of the Kingdom) are commanded, as vve alvvaies ought and ſhould; yet (as I have ſaid) vve muſt ſubmit our ſelves to the puniſhment vvhich ſhall be laid upon us; bad Magiſtrates are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and vve muſt receive our tryals vvith patience. VVe muſt look upon it as the juſt puniſhment of our iniquities, and vve muſt vvillingly accept of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus have you heard of the vvay and maner hovv vve are to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33980:10"/> the King. It follovvs next, that I ſhevv you vvhy vve are to Honour the King, vvhere you ſhall ſee that it is not an arbitrary thing, but a Duty of an abſolute neceſſity laid upon us. This vvill appear in theſe ſeven or eight things, vvhereby the excellencie of K ngs in regard of their outvvard condition above all others, may be ſeen.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Creation of Kings is from God, they are a ſpecial ſort of Men, raiſed up in a peculiar manner to their places by God, vvho pleads it as his glory, <hi>that Kings reign by him,</hi> Prov. 8. and Rom. 13.1. <hi>The Powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath communicated to Kings the Image of his ovvn Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and printed in the natures of men a natural form of Kings, as Vice-gerents to God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Divine Sentence is in the mouth of the King,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.10. their Judgment is Gods Judgment: and God vvould have the People to believe that vvhat they ſay in Judgment, God himſelf ſaith it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They take account of all other men, but are countable to none but to God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They are the Original, and Fountaine of all Honour, from them all the Honour which any of the Subjects have, flows, and ſo do all Offices of Honour, and Government in their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They are the Baſis, or the Foundation or Stay of all their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who are maintained in Religion, Juſtice, and Peace by their means.</p>
            <p n="7">7. God himſelf was a King, and is delighted to rank himſelf amongſt men of that degree: and as he takes to himſelf the name of a King, ſo Kings hath his Name again put upon them, for their greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> Pſalm 82.6. to wit Gods by Office; for they are Gods Deputies, and Vice-gerents here upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They have a power above all other men, therefore is that <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers,</hi> the words imports that the King is Superiour to all, he is Supreame, as <hi>Peter</hi> calls him verſ. 13. of this Chapter, the word ſignifies one that hath above the havings of other men, and ſo the King hath more then all his Subjects, not only in matter of mantenance, but alſo in matter of Authority and Supremacy. That the King is Supreame is ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33980:11"/> that it needs no poof. Princes therefore in the Old Teſtamant, are called Heads of the Tribes or of the People, to ſignifie that they were not only higher in place, but had a Soveraigne and a Supreame Authority over all the People, and therefore this Supremacy of Kings gives them Authority in all cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil. I do not ſay that the King by vertue of his Supremacy may determine of matters of Faith, and Doctrine, this is meerly Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, and belongs only to Eccleſiaſtical Perſons; nor do I ſay that the King may ſet up a Miniſtry in the Church, that for the ſubſtance of the calling was not inſtitute by Chriſt, from whom only all the Miniſters of the Goſpel have their miſſion, as is clear from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. Nor yet do I ſay that Kings by vertue of their Supremacy, may take upon them to execute the Office of a Church Miniſter, he may not Preach, nor adminiſter the Sacraments, nor execute Church-Cenſurs: This was the preſumption of <hi>Uzzias,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was juſtly puniſhed, and far leſſe hath he power to bring in Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Service into the Church as a part of Gods Worſhip; and therefore was <hi>Jeroboam</hi> condemned for the Calves, and <hi>Ahab</hi> for <hi>Baal,</hi> and <hi>Ahaz</hi> for the Altar at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and all the Kings for the High-places.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe it is evident, that the Kings Authority, may and ought to be extended in Spiritual things for the good of the Subject, and therefore in reſpect of Religion, they are ſaid to be Nurſing Fathers, and Nurſing Mothers. The Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. ſayes of the Magiſtrate, <hi>he is the Miniſter of God for thy good.</hi> Now the good of the Subject is not onely a Civil, but a Spiritual good, which is the greateſt, and therefore to be moſt ſought for by the Prince.</p>
            <p>Now then the Kings Authority, and Supremacy in things Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical may be ſo far extended.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He may, by his Laws enjoyn the Profeſſion of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Confeſſion of Faith according to the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He may provide according to his power, that the Churches be furniſhed with able Miniſters, and that they likewiſe have power to call, and ordain other Miniſters, to diſpoſe or depoſe as may be moſt for the good of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He may provide by his Laws, that the Word of God may be ſincerely, and purely taught, and the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33980:11"/> and the Cenſures of the Church executed according to the Word.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He may, forbid by his Laws, and accordingly puniſh Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Hereſies, Idolatrie, Sacriledge, and the like.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He may appoint and determine the Circumſtances of Gods Worſhip, which are not determined in the Word, as he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the time, place, and outward form of Prayer, Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, Faſting, Alms, or the like; For in reference to the External Regiment of the Church, the Supreame Gubernative Power is in the Supreame Magiſtrate. Theſe things muſt not be done tumultuouſly, or confuſedly, but in order, and that order the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may preſcribe.</p>
            <p>And as the Kings Authority and Supremacy is thus ſo far extended in Eccleſiaſtical thing, ſo alſo over Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, <hi>Every Soul must be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> and therefore if Church-men have Souls they muſt be ſubject alſo. We find that Princes have executed their Authoritie over Church-men, Examples whereof we have in the Word, as <hi>David</hi> appointed the Order, and Offices of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites. <hi>Solomon</hi> put down <hi>Abiather</hi> from the Prieſthood. <hi>Joſias</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the very bones of the Prieſts upon the Altar, and ſo purged the Temple, and reſtored the Paſſover. Chriſt himſelf was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Authoritie of Princes, and appeared at their Tribunal; <hi>Paul</hi> was ſubject and appeared before the Magiſtrates, and uſed their power when he appealed to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> For if Church-men be Citizens, or Members of the Commonwealth, then they muſt be ſubject to the Rulers, and Laws of the Commonwealth. To this alſo is the Doctrine of the pureſt times ſince the Apoſtles agreeable; for <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. ſayes, that all Church-men yea Apoſtles, Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and Prophets muſt be ſubject to the Secular Power. And <hi>Bernard</hi> reaſons out of that place thus. If every ſoul muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, then yours alſo that are Church-men; who hath excepted you from this all? If any man goes about to except you; he goes about to deceive you.</p>
            <p>Thus then in regard of all theſe, whereby the King Excellency eminently appears we are to honour him, and whoſoever will refuſe this, it is an evident token that the Devil who is the author of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and the Prince of Darkneſs, hath his chief reſidence, and dwelling in him.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33980:12"/>
            <p>I come now in the laſt place to give the Uſes of this Doctrine, which I ſhall perform with as great brevity as may be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> 1. And firſt, muſt we honour the King, as you have heard, then this ſerves to fetter the Romiſh Colt, which kicks at Princes with his heel, who will depoſe Kings and diſpoſe of their Kingdoms as he thinks good, and lifts up himſelf ſo high, as that he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the greateſt Princes in Chriſtendom, ſo far is he from giving that honour, which our Text requires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Again, to be condemned are the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and generally the whole body of the Fanaticks, who liking beſt an Anarchy, like untamed Horſes alſo lifts up their heels againſt Government; they will acknowledge no King, but <hi>King Jeſus:</hi> but certainly if they did acknowledge him, they would alſo acknowledge thoſe who are ſent of him; <hi>for all the Powers that he are ordained of God.</hi> As upon the one hand a Popular Government which they aime at is burdenſome, where in ſtead of one King many Kings are ſet up, which is a great Judgment, and hurts the Commonwealth, as when many Maſter-Pilots deſire to hold the Rudder they hinder one another, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Commonwealth where many will rule, unleſſe it be ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatly one under another, is like Plinies <hi>Amphiſbena,</hi> a Serpent, which had a head at each end of her body, and while both ſtrived which ſhould be the Maſter-head, the body was toyled miſerably and at length torn, and rent loathſomly. So upon the other ſide no King is a Judgment; for when there is no King, every one would be a King, one cauſe of great confuſion, and diſorder, as we to our ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieence have ſeen of late, when there was no King in our <hi>Iſraël,</hi> and therefore it may be noted as a juſt wonder, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. <hi>that the Graſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers have no King, yet they go forth by bands;</hi> for the body of the Commonwealth which wants a chief Ruler, is like the body of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphemus</hi> without an eye, and in ſuch a State, Men like Fiſhes dovour one another. But let the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and the reſt of that confuſed rable ſay, and pretend what they pleaſe againſt Kings, and chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, yet we ſee that in all their Inſurrections, and Rebellions, popular equality hath been alwaies burdenſom unto them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have alwaies appointed one to be Head over the reſt, who like <hi>Beelzebub</hi> amonſt the Devils guids, and rules all, as <hi>Cromwell</hi> that notable Impoſture, and Arch-Traitor did of late.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33980:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. Thirdly, Muſt we Honour the King, Then let every one of us inforce upon our own hearts an increaſe of care, and Conſcience in acknowledging the Honour and Right of Kings, and a loyal and ſincere obſervance, and obedience to their Laws. I think I need not uſe many motives to prove this, remember what I have ſaid, and you ſhall find them motives ſufficient; I ſhall ad a few more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Honour the King for the Lords ſake, which imports both the cauſe and maner of it. Kings are ordainded by God, and who is ſo blind, that may not ſee Gods miraculous hand in ſetting up our King, and therefore for his ſake, who hath thus ſet him up, honour, and obey him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath commanded that we ſhould Honour our King, therefore do it for the reſpect of that Duty we owe unto God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God hath indued him with a Soveraignty, and a great Majeſty, he hath ſubdued the People wonderfully under him, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blood, except of a few, who have periſhed in the gainſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> this Soveraignty, and Majeſty is Gods Image, this hath made him a little God upon earth, therefore Honour him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God hath been gratious to us in reſtoring our King, therefore for the love we bear to him, who hath laid upon us this Duty, let us in requital of his goodneſs obey him in Honouring the King.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Gods Glory will be much advanced, and our Profeſſion well ſpoken off, if we will Honour our King, and live as loyal, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Chriſtians, if not, we diſhonour God, and brings great ſtorms of wrath upon our ſelves by the fury of Princes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We muſt give an account to God for our cariage towards our King, as well as for our behaviour towards the Lord himſelf, let us therefore Honour our King.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Our King is bone of our bone, and fleſh, of our fleſh, he is of the ſame Proteſtant Religion with us, he hath been the greateſt Sufferer of all his People, this way every faithful Subject who has been a Sufferer in theſe times are intereſſed in the King: but I adde he hath been a Sufferer by his own, and for his own, and ſhall we not then for all this Honour him? Did he not ſtand immovable as a Rock againſt all temptations, to draw him to Popery during his Exile, and ſhould we not Honour him for this?</p>
            <p>Let us then indeavour by all means to give him all the Honour that is due unto him, no more to rebel againſt him, nor to aſſiſt by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33980:13"/> any meane, no not by advice or counſel any of his Enemies, but let us rather learn to ſubmit our ſelves unto him, and to obey him; for that is the chiefeſt Honour we can give unto him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us obey him from the heart, becauſe God has an Intereſt in this Service.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us obey him with fear, becauſe God will be an avenger of diſobedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though our Obedience, and Subjection ſhould be to our loſs or diſcredit, or hurt any way, yet for the Lords ſake we ſhould do it. If we thus obey him we Honour him, and by this means ſhall the Crown be long continued with him, and we, and our Poſterity ſhall enjoy many good dayes under his happy Reign and Government, which God grant. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>MIDDELBURGH, Printed by <hi>Thomas Berry,</hi> dwelling near the Engliſh Exchange. 1663.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33980:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
